<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Helpes to humiliation. By R.B.</title>
            <author>Bolton, Robert, 1572-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16327</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3235</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115297</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850516</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850516</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15724</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16327)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15724)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1440:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Helpes to humiliation. By R.B.</title>
                  <author>Bolton, Robert, 1572-1631.</author>
                  <author>I. S., fl. 1631-1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 164, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Turner, for Michael Sparke [in London], dwelling in Greene Arbor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R.B. = Robert Bolton.</note>
                  <note>Editor's preface signed: I.S.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Humility --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15724:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15724:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>HELPES TO HVMILIATION.</p>
            <p>By R. B.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>IAMES. 4.10.</bibl>
               <p>Humble your ſelues in the ſight of the Lord, and hee ſhall lift you vp.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD.</hi> Printed by <hi>William Turner,</hi> for <hi>Michael Sparke,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Greene Arbor.</hi> 1631.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15724:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15724:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Here commend vnto thee Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader a table of Repentance, now put into a little Tract, collected from that graue, learned, &amp; godly Divine, <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Bolton.</hi> I could haue beene content to
<pb facs="tcp:15724:3"/>
haue ſtayed the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, vntill ſuch time, in which the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor might haue beene prevailed with to print it; for there cannot but want much beauty and luſtre which it might haue had, if it had been ſet forth or peruſed to be fitted for the Preſſe by him that firſt gaue life vnto it; but being inforced to it by the importunity of many well affected, both farre
<pb facs="tcp:15724:3"/>
and neere; &amp; I vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to haue ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious fountaine ſealed vp, conſidering the good that might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to many in the meane time by it. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued by the Authors leaue no longer to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſe the ſame to a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate vſe, but to impart it to a publike good, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially conſidering, firſt, how few are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the right nature of Humiliation,
<pb facs="tcp:15724:4"/>
and Repentance, no more than <hi>Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> was with regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: that though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny boaſt of it, few haue it, when alas it's plaine, without true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance there is no ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now this table having ſo perspicuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnſolded the nature of this grace, thoſe that haue a beginning of it, may from hence adde an increaſe to their ſtore; and they that
<pb facs="tcp:15724:4"/>
want it, may here ſee the way and meanes of obtaining it. Secondly, the extraordinary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of faſting and prayer, a duty of preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous account amongſt Gods Children, which hath alwayes beene wonderfully bleſt with a happy ſucceſſe, in ſo much, as albeit their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary prayers returne not empty without a bleſſing, yet reſpectiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to thoſe prayers
<pb facs="tcp:15724:5"/>
which are joyned with faſting, they ſeeme bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren and blasted, which otherwiſe are fruitfull and full eared. How then could I withhold this which by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and the judgement of judicious Chriſtians, cannot but bee of ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all vſe and helpe vnto ſuch a bleſſed and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefull ordinance? Thirdly, theſe times call for it, to faſt and pray and cry mightily vnto
<pb facs="tcp:15724:5"/>
God by our prayers, that wee may ſtand in the gappe, and make vp the breach: and from this little Tract wee may receiue much helpe in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. VVherefore I hope I ſhall neede no further perſwaſion for thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious acceptance, than that hereby if the fault be not thine owne, thou mayest receiue much good and comfort to thy ſoule: which if thou
<pb facs="tcp:15724:6"/>
findest, giue God the glory, the Author thy thankes, and mee thy prayers. ⁂</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I.S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15724:6"/>
            <head>HELPES TO HVMILIATION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Actes 2.37.</bibl>
                  <p>Now when they heard this, they were pricked in their heart, and ſaid vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N THESE words here is: Firſt a compunction and a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15724:7"/>
thorow wounding their hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, a conſul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation what to doe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>Peters</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly counſell; <hi>Amend your liues and be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the firſt, in that theſe men when they had heard of the greatnes of their ſinne, were thus wounded at the heart; obſerue:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Point. </seg>
               </label> That contrition in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15724:7"/>
a new creature ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily is anſwerable to his former vanity.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtan. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Manaſſe,</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.6. <hi>Mary Magdalen, Luke</hi> 7. <hi>Augustine</hi> a great ſinner, wrote 12 bookes of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> To whom much is forgiuen, they loue much: and this is a fountaine of Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall Repentance. As a traitor condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to dye, receiuing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15724:8"/>
a pardon would wonderfully breake his heart to thinke hee ſhould be ſo vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanous to ſo gratious a Prince: ſo it is with a Chriſtian that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds Gods mercy to him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Chriſtians after their converſion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee their ſinnes to the vtmoſt, with all the circumſtances that make them hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as the object,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15724:8"/>
nature, perſon, time, &amp; age, &amp;c. in which, or how they were done, that ſo they may be more hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for them.</p>
            <p>If it be not ſo (as it may be otherwiſe, for God is a free a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and is not tyed to any proportion of ſorrow) then ſuch troubles as theſe vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſeaze on them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, they are often
afflicted with this,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15724:9"/>
that their converſion is not through and ſound, and ſo do not with ſuch heartines and chearefulneſſe performe the duties of Godlineſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they are many times haunted with liſtleſſeneſſe &amp; coldneſſe in their progreſſe of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, they are viſited with ſome croſſe or other that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15724:9"/>
ſtickes by them: to make them lay a greater Load vpon ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, they are more ſubject to be overtaken with their ſweete ſin, becauſe they haue no more ſorrowed for it. For the leſſe it is ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, the more it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnares men.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, ſome of them haue beene aſſault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon their bed of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15724:10"/>
death with ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſtrong temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: Not that men ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this is alwayes the reaſon of it; for God hath ends in all his workes, knowne only to himſelfe; but thus I haue knowne ſome haue beene troubled, and this may be in great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to make a weake converſion more ſtrong. Leſt any
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15724:10"/>
Chriſtian ſhould be troubled at it, take notice in Contrition:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> There muſt be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of heart becauſe of ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> There muſt bee a diſlike of it in the will.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> There muſt be a tranſmentation or ſtrong reaſoning in the minde out of the word of God againſt ſinne. This is the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new of Repentance
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15724:11"/>
as <hi>Auſtin</hi> had againſt Playes, that all men could not draw him to them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> There muſt be a reſolution and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and watching againſt it, as <hi>Iob</hi> with his eye. <hi>Iob</hi> 31.1</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> There muſt be a grieuing that hee is not excellent in all theſe, and herein hee muſt make vp what hee wanteth in the former. Theſe be in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15724:11"/>
ſome meaſure in all Chriſtians; ſome are more eminent in one part, ſome in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had little ſorrow, but a ſtrong Reſolution, becauſe hee had ſoe ſtrong a temptation, and withſtood it; hee had ſtrong reaſons beyond nature to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ſinne, and reſolue againſt it, ſo that it is not ſo much the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as the truth of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15724:12"/>
every part that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. But if they be not in an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency in great ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, they are to mourne for the want of them. To helpe herein, obſerue theſe tenne degrees or Acts of repentance or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther helpes to Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Act. </seg>1</label> Get a ſight, and ſurvey, and full ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of all thy vileneſſe, iniquities,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15724:12"/>
tranſgreſſions, and ſinne, the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and nature of them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Act. </seg>2</label> Get a right appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of GODS wrath and fiery in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, and the pure eye of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Act. </seg>3</label> Get a ſenſe of the vnſpeakeable miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thou art lyable to by reaſon of ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Act. </seg>3</label> Get a baſe eſteeme of thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:15724:13"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Act. </seg>5</label> Get an inward ſorrow of heart and bleeding of ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Act. </seg>6</label> Get an outward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing with heart-peircing confeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Act. </seg>7</label> Get an hatred and averſion in thy will from ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Act. </seg>8</label> Get a ſtrong rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning in thy minde againſt ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Act. </seg>9</label> Get a ſincere op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in thy life, to ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Act. </seg>10</label> Get a ſincere grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15724:13"/>
that thou canſt doe theſe things no better. Now for the firſt Act, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Act. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>(viz.)</hi> Get a ſight and ſurvey, and full apprehenſion of all thy vileneſſe, ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſinnes, the number and nature of them; for which purpoſe take theſe three helpes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>1</label> Firſt, keepe the eye of thy naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience cleare.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15724:14"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>2</label> Secondly, be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with all the wayes thou canſt poſſible to anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mize thy ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the guilt of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall ſin, becauſe a Chriſtian may haue his heart locked vp more at one time then at another.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>1</label> For the firſt of which (viz.) the keeping of the eye of the naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15724:14"/>
cleare, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt the rules of the Heathen that never did know Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments of the Heathen.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon notions of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which were in the Heathen.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the firſt <hi>(viz)</hi> The rules of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then that never did<note place="margin">The rules of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>then.</note>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:15724:15"/>
know Chriſt, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> in: Lying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the word of God which baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it from Heauen,<note place="margin">Revel. 22.21.</note> by the light of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſon <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſayth, A lye is evill in it ſelfe, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee diſpenſed withall; and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it is this: wee haue a tongue giuen vs to expreſſe the truth; now if our tongue tell more or
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15724:15"/>
leſſe then our minde conceiues, it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt nature.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Ribald talking, of which many make a ſport, and rather then they will loſe a Ieſt, they will ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to damne their ſoules. <hi>Epictetus</hi> ſaith, It's dangerous to digreſſe into ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenity of ſpeech.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Cowardize in good cauſes, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it good ſleeping
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15724:16"/>
in a whole skinne, <hi>Ariſtotle Ethic.</hi> 3. cap. 1. that in ſome caſes a man had better loſe his life then be cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Drunkenneſſe; the dayes be ſo drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in impiety, that if a man be not drunke every day, hee will take it in a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace if hee be not counted an honeſt man; whereas <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> ſayth it is but a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15724:16"/>
raging madneſſe, &amp; if hee ſhould behaue himſelfe ſo but two or three dayes, as he doth when hee is drunke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, men would count him mad.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Mourning immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately for loſſe of wife or children.<note place="margin">Sene. 100. ep.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Paſſions of anger; Morall <hi>Philoſophers</hi> haue many excellent rules, the which if a naturall man would take notice of, hee
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15724:17"/>
would never be ſo paſſionate, for they ſay it ariſeth firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> From a great weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpirit. For were hee manly, hee would paſſe by thoſe things with ſcorne: whereas he ſhewes himſelfe to be of an effeminate ſpirit and impotent affections. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> From ſelfe-loue. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> From an over deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy and too much niceneſſe in ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15724:17"/>
wrong. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> From a paſſing proud na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, being affraid to be contemned. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> From too much credulity, ſo that if one or two doe whiſper, hee thinkes they ſpeake ſomething hurtfull of him, and is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to breake out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to rage: for which paſſions they giue theſe rules.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thy body and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15724:18"/>
tongue in quiet.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> That thou ſay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Greeke <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabet</hi> before thou ſay any thing in rage.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> That thou looke thy ſelfe in a glaſſe, and thou ſhalt ſee what an vgly crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thou art in that rage; for ſayth <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> his eyes ſparkle like fire, his heart ſwels, his pulſe beates, &amp;c. ſo that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15724:18"/>
if in this moode hee ſhould ſee himſelfe in a glaſſe he would never againe be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <label>The en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovvments of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>then.</label> Secondly, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance. </seg>1</label> For inſtance, <hi>Regulus</hi> the <hi>Romane,</hi> being taken priſoner of his enemies the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> and vpon promiſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne if he ſped not, obtaining to goe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15724:19"/>
home to <hi>Rome</hi> to treate with the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate for a commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Captiues, <hi>Carthaginians</hi> for <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,</hi> of whom himſelfe was one: Comming to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, he gaue weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty reaſons to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them from commutation; ſo as chuſing rather to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide the certaine cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of his enemies, then to breake his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15724:19"/>
faith and promiſe; hee returned, where hee was moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly vſed of them; by whoſe example Chriſtians might be aſhamed that make no matter of break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their promiſes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Fabricius</hi> attained to that height of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, that it was ſayd, A man may as ſoone pull the Sunne from its Spheare, as that man from his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15724:20"/>
honeſt and juſt dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Cato</hi> was ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, that it is ſayd; hee did not good for feare, ſhame, profit, &amp;c. but becauſe goodnes was ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated into him, that hee could not doe otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>Cambyſes</hi> ſtood ſo ſtricktly againſt bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, that a Iudge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken in that crime, hee flayed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15724:20"/>
him, and ſet his skinne in the ſeate of Iuſtice, and let his ſon leane thereon that hee might hate that vice.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtance. </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>Zaleuchus</hi> King of the <hi>Locrians,</hi> made a law for adultery, that whoſoever was taken in that fact ſhould haue his eyes pulled out; now his owne ſonne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken in that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15724:21"/>
fault firſt, becauſe he would not violate his own decree, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out one of his ſonnes eyes, and one of his owne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <label>Common notions in Heathen.</label> Thirdly, obſeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the common notions of nature, which were in the Heathen as,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> All good is to be done.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> All evill is to be avoided.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Kinde is to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:15724:21"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Do as we would be done by.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> God is to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence ariſeth this objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, namely:<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaeſt. </seg>
               </label> Is not this notion extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed in them that deny God?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Not vtterly, but it generally dwels in them; ſo farre onely they haue vſe of it, as to leaue them without excuſe, <hi>Rom.</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:15724:22"/>
1.19.20.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> A mans life is to be preſerued: Now ſelfe preſervation is ſoe ingrafted into the blood &amp; veines; that therefore the ſelfe-murderer ſinneth:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Againſt God the Father.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againſt God the Sonne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Againſt God the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Againſt the light of nature.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:15724:22"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <label>Againſt God the Father.</label>  For the firſt, <hi>(viz.)</hi> thou ſinneſt againſt God the Father, who commandeth, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> and ſoe thou ſinneſt:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Againſt the image of God, in that thou deſtroyeſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againſt his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty; for,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Hee hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thee to worke in his vineyard, and thou wilt rather dye, &amp;c. as if hee were
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15724:23"/>
a hard Maſter, that thou dareſt ſtay no longer in his ſeruice.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Thou diſhonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt him, and gratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt his enemy.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Hee hath planted thee as a tenant at will in this earthly tabernacle, and thou beateſt it about thy eares.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <label>Againſt God the Sonne.</label> Thou ſinneſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God the Son; for,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Thou art none of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15724:23"/>
thine owne, thou art bought with aprice: this will helpe thee againſt the Divels temptations; for when hee comes to tempt thee to that ſinne, ſay, thou art an others 'and not thine owne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Thou maymeſt Chriſts body in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <label>Againſt God the Holy Ghoſt.</label> Thou ſinneſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God the holy
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15724:24"/>
Ghoſt; for,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Thou polluteſt thy ſoule with blood; and,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It is the office of the Spirit to dwell with vs: and</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> It is the office of the Spirit to invite vs to taſte of the good bleſſings of God, as <hi>Eſay</hi> 51. Oh! <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> but my ſoule is blacke with ſinne,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> &amp;c. This is the action of the Spirit to reveale this vnto
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15724:24"/>
thee.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <label>Againſt the light of nature.</label> Thou ſinneſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture moſt cowardly, and againſt forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; thou ſinneſt againſt the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; againſt thy neighbour, thy fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and thy ſelfe; and putteſt thy ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſorrowes of the divels which is a Bedlam mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>2</label> Be acquainted with
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15724:25"/>
all the wayes thou canſt poſſibly, how to anatomize thy ſinnes; for which purpoſe take theſe methods and helpes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Method. </seg>1</label> Bee perfect in the Law of God, and looke thy ſelfe in the pure Chriſtall glaſſe thereof: be through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly catechiſed in the Commandements, as in the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conſider.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:15724:25"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Preparation.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Celebration.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Preparation, which conſiſts,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In praying:</p>
            <p>Publiquely with thy Family; Privately with thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In examination.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In renewing thy repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> In covenanting with thy thoughts to ſpend that whole day in holy things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Celebration.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:15724:26"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> It may be for ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous ſinnes in thy life thou haſt beene ſorrowfull, but thou haſt paſſed the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath with many wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings; for which thou haſt not beene humbled: All theſe are to be brought to thy minde with much bleeding.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> An vtter Ceſſation or abſtinence from thoughts, words, &amp; deeds; of calling, or
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15724:26"/>
recreation; more then for neceſſity, mercy, or comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Method. </seg>2</label> Take ſurvey of all the wrong which wee haue offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to all things in Heaven and Earth; all things are the worſe for a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man, ſoe farre as his ſinne can adde hurt vnto them</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Method. </seg>3</label> Take a peruſall of thy ſelfe from top to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15724:27"/>
toe. The ſinnes of thy eyes: each thing thou lookeſt on, not making a holy vſe of them, is a ſinne of omiſſion: conſider then how many there are every day, and, if in one part ſo many, what are there in the whole body?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Method. </seg>4</label> Conſider all the commiſſions, and omiſſions as thou ſtandeſt in ſeverall
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15724:27"/>
relations.</p>
            <p>As a Creature, how thou haſt car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried thy ſelfe to thy Creator.</p>
            <p>As an husband to thy wife.</p>
            <p>As a Father to thy Children.</p>
            <p>As a Maſter to thy Family.</p>
            <p>As a neighbour, to them without, or to Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <p>As a Subject, &amp;c.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15724:28"/>
Take notice of all thy faylings in all theſe, and thou ſhalt finde ſufficient mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for a day of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Method. </seg>5</label> Labour to get (as I am perſwaded eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſtian hath) two Catalogues of thy ſins, before con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and ſince.</p>
            <p>Of Gods mercies, ſpirituall and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>3</label> Take notice of the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15724:28"/>
guilt of originall ſinne. Now becauſe a Chriſtian may haue his heart lock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp more at one time then at an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, let them in caſe of barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, conſider theſe ſixe quickning points.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quick. Point. </seg>1</label> Looke to the ſeede, and ſinke, and naturall inclination of thy heart to all manner of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15724:29"/>
for ſuppoſe by the mercy of God thou wert able to ſay, and that truely, that thou couldeſt not poſſibly finde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny actuall ſin with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thee: yet looke backe to the corrupt fountaine, and there thou ſhalt finde that thou and the moſt holy Chriſtian on earth, whilſt thou li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt in this houſe of fleſh and tabernacle
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15724:29"/>
of clay, thou haſt it in thy nature to ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt, to kill Ieſus Chriſt, to commit ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domy; and what hindereth but Gods free mercy? This then throughly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, is ſufficient matter to humble thee, to conſider with thy ſelfe what a wretch am I yet, that haue this ſeede ſtill in my bowels.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:15724:30"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quic. Point. </seg>2</label> Conſider and throughly weigh the circumſtances of all thy ſinnes, of thy vnregeneration, at what time, in what place, with what ſcandall, &amp;c. As <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſayth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, hee did won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully weepe in reading the fourth booke of <hi>Virgill</hi> when <hi>Dido</hi> was kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; what a damn'd ſoule had I (quoth
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15724:30"/>
hee) that could weepe for her miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and not for my owne? ſo when hee liſtned to muſicke, and to the tune in ſinging of a Pſalme in the Church, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then kept his heart to goe along with the matter: and for being much addicted to ſtage-playes, and many more, but eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for robbing an
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15724:31"/>
orchard, which hee aggravates by many circumſtances; that great renowned Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther left this exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to all poſterity; whereas if a young man now adayes ſhould but crye out of robbing an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard, hee would be thought ſimple and too preciſe. Looke the ſecond booke of his Confeſſions,<note place="margin">Cap. 4.</note> where ſee his ſinne
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15724:31"/>
aggravated, by theſe ten circumſtances.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Circum∣ſtance. </seg>1</label> Sayth hee, this theft which I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted was not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the booke of God forbidden, but I had it in my heart dayly.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Circum∣ſtance. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Volui, feci</hi> I reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with free will to doe it, and I did it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Circum∣ſtance. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Faſtidio aequitatis,</hi> I did not doe it for want, but in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine of goodneſſe,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15724:32"/>
and out of an eager deſire to do wrong.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Circum∣ſtance. </seg>4</label> I had abundance of the ſame kinde &amp; better at home.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Circum∣ſtance. </seg>5</label> I did ſteale them, not ſoe much to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the thing, as mine owne theft, that it might be ſayd of my old compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that I robd an Orchard.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Circum∣ſtance. </seg>6</label> There was a number of deſperate ſwaggerers and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15724:32"/>
Divels with mee.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Circum∣ſtance. </seg>7</label> 
               <hi>Nocte intempeſtiva,</hi> at midnight: which hee aggravates with another Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, when wee had been ſporting and dancing, and drinking we did it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Circum∣ſtance. </seg>8</label> We carried al away.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Circum∣ſtance. </seg>9</label> We carried ſo many away, that they were a burden to vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Circum∣ſtance. </seg>10</label> When wee came home we gaue them
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15724:33"/>
to the ſwine: and then at the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hee cryes, <hi>Oh my God, behold my heart, Ecce cor meum Deus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If wee would looke backe on ſuch a Sabbath breaking, how in ſuch a place, at ſuch a time, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed, with luſt; If drunkards, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, vſurers, &amp;c. would take this courſe, they might finde ſuch aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15724:33"/>
that by the mercy of God, might terrifie them from their evill courſes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quic. Point. </seg>3</label> In caſe of barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe conſider, wee had our hands in the ſinne of <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſoe brought all the ſorrow, ſinne, and damnation vpon all men that are or ſhall be damned, and we are guilty of all the horrours of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; If wee had not
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15724:34"/>
hearts of adamant, or hewn out of a rocke, or had ſucked the breſt of Wolues or Tigers, wee would be moued at this, which is able to breake a thouſand adamants. I ſpeake adviſedly, it is able to open a wide gap of penitent teares in the moſt flinty ſoule of the moſt bloody ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quic. Point. </seg>4</label> Cut of all ſin both
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15724:34"/>
originall and actuall that thou haſt taken notice of, and do but conſider the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections that follow the beſt actions, the innumerable diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the moſt holy prayer that ever thou madeſt; the ſins of the laſt Sabbath, thy deadneſſe, fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quic. Point. </seg>5</label> Remoue all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall ſinnes, yet conſider how many
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15724:35"/>
wayes wee haue our hands in others ſins, which (it may be) they haue carried to hell with them. Wee haue a world of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from hence to breake our hearts: for wee may be guilty of others ſins 13 wayes; There is none but are guilty of ſome of theſe wayes. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, by incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them, as thoſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15724:35"/>
Prophets which cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Peace, peace,</hi> when there is no peace, when they are but formall or civill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, thoſe that ſow pillowes vnder mens elbowes, that heale the wounds of the people with faire words, when there is nothing towards,<note place="margin">Eſa. 9.5. Eze. 13.10. Ier. 14.14.</note> but tumbling gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in blood, and vengeance, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring with fire.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15724:36"/>
Aske all thoſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that reveale not the whole counſell of God, who ſent them to incourage; it ſhall all fall to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; but you of this place are inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for wherin haue I hid any thing from you? no, I dare not be guilty of any mans blood that way for the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my ſoule.</p>
            <p>By provoking; as
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15724:36"/>
               <hi>Iob's</hi> wife ſayd to him, <hi>Curſe God &amp; dye:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 2.9.</note> ſo,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>Fathers provoke not your Children to wrath,</hi> for they then are guilty of their ſins</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> By familiarity with ſinners, with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany keeping. If thou vouchſafeſt thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany to Alehouſe haunters, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, to Gods ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; looke for that ſharpe checke which
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15724:37"/>
the Prophet gaue to <hi>Iehoſophat</hi> for aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating himſelfe with wicked <hi>Ahab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chron. 20.37.</note> ſaying <hi>Shouldeſt thou counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the vngodly, &amp; loue them that hate the Lord? Therefore is wrath vpon thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord.</hi> Or as <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 50.18. <hi>VVhen thou ſaweſt a theefe, thou conſentedſt with him, and haſt beene partakers with adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers.</hi> Therefore as
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15724:37"/>
               <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſayd to the people, <hi>Separate your ſelues from the Tents of</hi> Corah, <hi>leaſt ye pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh with them.</hi> And, <hi>Come out of Babylon, my people, haue no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with that VVhore, lest yee periſh in her ſinnes, and be destroyed with her plagues,</hi> Rev. 18. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſayth, <hi>I haue not dwelt with vaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, nor will I haue fellowſhip with the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15724:38"/>
Odi Eccleſiam malignantium.</hi> And who would vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to let their loue runne on ſuch in this life, from whom they muſt be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the world to come? But for works of thy particular cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, as bying, ſelling, ſalutations, &amp;c. wee muſt haue theſe, or we muſt out of this world, as 1. <hi>Co</hi> 5.10.11</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> By participation,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15724:38"/>
               <hi>Thy Princes are rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; companions of theues:</hi> ſo Magiſtrates which execute not their office, are guilty of all the ſins which the people commit within the compaſſe of the time of their governement, and they are all ſet on their ſcore, without repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> By ſilence when thou heareſt a good man traduced &amp; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:15724:39"/>
nothing; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dumbe dogges; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Sabbath is a bloody day to them, for their ſilence is cauſe of all the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities done that day, and all theſe things which they doe amiſſe, whether by ſwearing, Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe haunting, &amp;c. all are ſet on their ſcore: ſo all thoſe that ore faint and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly for Gods
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15724:39"/>
glory and truth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> By defending,<note place="margin">Eſa. 5.20.</note>
               <hi>VVoe to them that call darkneſſe light, and light darknes;</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any by quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of wit will la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to maintaine vſury, bribery, &amp;c. they are all guilty of thoſe ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> By Counſelling,<note place="margin">1 Kings 21.7.</note> as <hi>Ieſabell</hi> counſelled her husband to kill <hi>Naboth.</hi> Or as thoſe who ſay, <hi>Come, let vs
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15724:40"/>
crowne our ſelues with roſe buds before they be withered,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wiſ. 2 9</note> 
               <hi>let vs all be partaker of our wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 11.15.</note>By commanding, as <hi>David</hi> command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Vriah</hi> to be ſet in the ſore-front of the battell, and therefore guilty of his death.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> By commending,<note place="margin">Act 12.22.</note> as thoſe that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended <hi>Herod</hi> for his oration, ſaying, <hi>It is the voice of a God;</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:15724:40"/>
they were guilty of his ſin in taking ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour from God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> By connivency,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 3.13.</note> as
<hi>Ely</hi> winked at his ſons; for Which you may ſee what a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full judgement fell vpon that houſe for forbearing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If we had no other ſins in a day of humiliation, it were able to breake the hardeſt heart; but eſpecially for Maiſters of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15724:41"/>
who winke at their children and ſervants ſwearing, Sabboath breaking, &amp;c. If theſe be not guilty of the former ſinnes, yet they are guilty in not praying with them &amp; bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary exerciſes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> By conſenting;<note place="margin">Acts 22.20.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> bewayled that hee carried the cloathes of them that ſlew <hi>Stephen</hi> when
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15724:41"/>
hee was ſtoned.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> By not ſorrowing for them:<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.136. Pſal. 25.13. Mar. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> ſhewes what Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ought to doe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> By not praying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, for the ſuppreſſing of them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quic. Point. </seg>6</label> Conſider the ſins of the times: <hi>Davids</hi> eyes guſh out with teares to ſee men tranſgreſſe the Law.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.136.</note> Soe <hi>Lots</hi> heart was vexed dayly with the ſinnes of the people
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15724:42"/>
amongſt whom hee liued, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8. And <hi>bleſſed are they that mourne,</hi> ſo <hi>Math.</hi> 5.4. Obſerue theſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall branches well, &amp; thou ſhalt finde ſins enow to mourne for.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Second Act.</label> Now for the 2 Act. <hi>viz.</hi> A right appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of Gods wrath and fierce in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the pure eye of God againſt ſin. Now the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15724:42"/>
oftentimes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines, that hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not apprehend Gods wrath ſufficiently. Let him take theſe helpes</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>1</label> The ſeverity of Gods Iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin; for which</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> He threw downe the Angels fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to be Divels for ever, (which might haue done him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of glory) and that, as ſome
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:15724:43"/>
thinke but for a thought.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For but eating an apple, which ſome count a ſmall fault, hee caſt <hi>Adam</hi> out of Paradice, and ſent a world of miſery v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him and his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Hee drowned the world;<note place="margin">Gen 7.</note> which ſhews the infinite purity in God not to abide ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Hee burnt <hi>Sodome</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:15724:43"/>
for thoſe very ſinnes now reigning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs.<note place="margin">Ezec. 16.49.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Hee rejected the <hi>Iewes</hi> which were his moſt deare peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: for they ſoe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked GOD, that they are now no na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and his wrath hath ſo fiercely ſeiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on them, that they are moſt curſed va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabonds, and ſoe haue beene a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſixe hundred
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:15724:44"/>
yeares.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Conſider, he hath created horrour of conſcience which is a hell vpon earth for the puniſhment of ſin; but aboue all, the torments of hell, that woefull place and ſtate prepared for the wicked, where the greater part of the world ſhall be how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>2</label> Conſider how hard a thing it is to get
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15724:44"/>
pardon for ſinne, in that the Iuſtice of God, was hard to be ſatisfied. Imagine all the world were tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a maſſe or lumpe of gold, the ſtones of the ſtreetes into precious pearles, and the Sea and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers all flowing with liquid ſtreames of moſt pure gold:<note place="margin">Mic. 6, 7.</note> they would not ſatisfie the wrath of God for the leaſt ſinne: if all
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15724:45"/>
the Angels and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in heaven and earth had joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and made one fervent prayer for mans ſinne, nay if they had offered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to haue beene annihilated, it could never haue beene effected; nay if the Sonne of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhould haue ſupplicated his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt intreaties, hee
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:15724:45"/>
could not haue been heard vnleſſe he had taken our fleſh vpon him, and ſuffered what divels &amp; men could imagine to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict vpon him. Which well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, there is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite cauſe to bring vs to a ſenſe of Gods wrath, that he ſhould lay, and ſuffer ſuch infinite torments to be on him, that hee cryes out vnto God,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:15724:46"/>
               <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken mee?</hi> Though hee loued him infinitely as himſelfe, yet hee would haue his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>3</label> The vnreſiſtable comming of God againſt ſinners, though hee is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull ready and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to be intreated whilſt hee vouchſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a day of viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; But if men will
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:15724:46"/>
withſtand the day, then he comes in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring rage; and his wrath being once kindled ſhall burne to the bottome of hell; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Arrowes ſhall drinke blood and eate fleſh, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13.8. then will hee meete them as a Beare robbed of her whelpes, &amp; teare in pieces when there is none to helpe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.2. And <hi>Eſay</hi> 66.15.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15724:47"/>
is ſet downe the manner of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, with fire and Chariots like a whirlewinde.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>4</label> Gods holineſſe, which oppoſeth ſin, and is contrary to it, that hee lookes not on the leaſt ſinne with the leaſt allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Third Act.</label> Get a ſenſe of the vnſpeakeable miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thou art lyable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by reaſon of ſinne;
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:15724:47"/>
for which purpoſe conſider all thy ſins, with their circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as of times, paſt, preſent, and to come.<note place="margin">Time paſt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Looke backe vpon all thy ſinnes paſt that ever thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittedſt, all thou haſt beene guilty of ever ſince thou waſt borne, originall, or actuall, knowne, or vnknowne, of thought, word and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:15724:48"/>
deede; They are written with a pen of iron, and with the point of a diamond, not to be raced out: they are all vpon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and now lye as ſo many ſleeping Lyons, gathering ſtrength and vigour againſt ſuch time as the Lord ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and then they will appeare &amp; rent thy ſoule in pieces.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:15724:48"/>
I ſay, let naturall men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider of this point, and they ſhall ſee themſelues miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; for there are ſome for a ſmall ſin put to ſuch frights, as they could not be comforted in a long ſpace; as ſome who hauing an adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous project, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any actual pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and others who hauing found a trifle, and made no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:15724:49"/>
to reſtore it; by the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall conſcience, knowing they did not as they would be done by, were put into vnſpeakable horrour; and ſome who hauing an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy thought of God, were put into ſuch amazement, that they wiſht they had never beene. If theſe for ſuch ſmall things (in mens ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count)
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:15724:49"/>
haue come to ſuch a paſſe, that they tooke no delight in any earthly thing, but are put to their wits end, ready to make away themſelues, wiſhing themſelues <hi>annihilated;</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what tearing of haire, what horrour of conſcience will ſeize vpon thee on thy bed of death: with what a gaſhly counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance wilt thou
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:15724:50"/>
looke vpon that blacke and helliſh Catalogue of all thy ſins? as lies, oathes, raylings, ſcoffings, at Gods people, rotten ſpeeches; bedlam paſſions, goods ill gotten, time ill ſpent, prophanatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boaths, and killing Chriſt at every Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, as all natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall men doe: Theſe ſhall be ſummoned before thee; &amp; charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:15724:50"/>
vpon thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence by the juſt God; then conſider in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion what horror will be in thine heart; no heart can conceiue it, nor tongue of men and Angels vtter it. Now then attend, and let none bleſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues &amp; ſay, I never felt this miſery, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſhall never hurt mee; I tell the; it is the perfection of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:15724:51"/>
thy miſery that thou art inſenſible of it: to be ſoule-ſicke and feele it not, is the complement of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie; and the reaſons why thou canſt not ſee it, are theſe ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> The divell, while thou art his, will not trouble thee; hee is a Politician of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſixe thouſand yeares experience, &amp; knowes if once thou
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:15724:51"/>
ſee thy ſinnes hee ſhall looſe thee; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee blindes thee.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Thy conſcience is lull'd aſleepe with carnall pleaſure, and worldly content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> A bucket of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is heavy on earth, in its owne place it is not ſoe. When men are meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly naturall, ſinne is in its owne place,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:15724:52"/>
and the weight is not felt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> The conſcience of a naturall man is like a wolfe in a mans body, while its fed with carnall friends, good fellowſhip, ſome great buſines of the world, &amp;c. its quiet; but take this away, and then its felt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>5</label> A naturall man is ſpiritually dead,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.1.</note> &amp; a dead man feeles no
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:15724:52"/>
weight you know.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>6</label> Hee lookes on ſin through falſe glaſſes, as vpon covetouſnes &amp; vſury, through the glaſſe of good huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry; ſo prodigali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty through the glaſſe of liberality.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>7</label> For want of conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; If we would by our ſelues conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der when the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter preſſeth Sabbath breaking, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinne, and ſay,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:15724:53"/>
this is my caſe, but now by the mercy of God I will be humbled; this would much helpe vs to ſee our miſery.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Thou haſt had thy hand in murthering many a ſoule; all thy drunken compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, thy brethren in iniquity, many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt converſed are dead, and in hell long agoe; thou art
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:15724:53"/>
guilty of the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their ſoules. <hi>Cain</hi> was a curſed man, &amp; had a brand vpon him for killing but a man, then how will the murthering of ſoe many ſoules affright thee, if thou haſt beene a meanes to ſet them to Hell? as</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For thy wife; thou ſhouldſt haue liued with her as a man of knowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:15724:54"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For thy Children; thou ſhouldſt haue catechiſed them, and brought them vp in religion.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> For thy ſervants, it may be thy example hath made them ſwear, lye, &amp;c: How wil their ſoules curſe thee in the pitte of hell, and curſe that time, that ever they firſt ſaw thee? but no carnall man will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue this till they
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:15724:54"/>
feele it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thou haſt beene the ſlaue of Sathan, worſe then a Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Gally-ſlaue all thy life; for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou mighteſt haue beene Gods Free-man, and wouldeſt not, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell hath bid thee lye, ſweare, breake Gods ſabboath, &amp;c. &amp; thou haſt obeyed him, and beene thee divels drudge. The Turkiſh fetters are
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:15724:55"/>
but cold iron at the worſt, but thine be inviſible chaines of eternall damnation: Hee ſcourgeth thy naked ſoule with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible ſcorpions, feeds thee every day with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone; When thou art out of the Turkiſh ſlavery, thou mayeſt be a man againe: but here Sathan ſcourgeth thee and thou ſeeſt it not; hee
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:15724:55"/>
feedeth thee with poyſon, and thou ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteſt it not: And ſhortly he will locke thee vp in perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all torments, where thou ſhalt never be freede from Divels.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">For pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time.</note> now thou art in health, thou thinkeſt all is well; but know to the contrary, whilſt thou art but natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and vnconver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:15724:56"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Thou doſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt God in a high degree, thou provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt the glory of his pure eye every day by every ſinne thou committeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Thou trampleſt vnder foote the blood of Chriſt in every Sacrament, if thou beeſt not a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The Spirit puts good motions into thy heart; as at this
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:15724:56"/>
time it may be, thou reſolueſt by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God to leaue all thy former wayes, and be Gods ſervant: but preſently thou ſtifleſt it by worldly talke, and thy old companions.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The Angels offer to guard thee, but thou refuſeſt their attendance, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeſt to be vnder their protection, while thou wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreſt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:15724:57"/>
out of thy wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> To Gods children thou art as a goade in their ſides.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Thou draweſt wife and children, neighbours and all thou canſt to Hell, by thy ill example, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The creatures thou art mercileſſe vnto, for thy ſin addes to their miſery which they groane vnder; and thou yet addeſt
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:15724:57"/>
to their burden by thy ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Thou art lyable to all the ill a man vnconverted may indure, or to any ſin that a man deſtitute of divine grace may commit as,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> To ſpirituall hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of minde, ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very vnder thy luſts, ſearedneſſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſinne againſt
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:15724:58"/>
the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> To temporall; any thing that may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall any man,<note place="margin">For time to come.</note> as to be poſſeſſed of the divell, &amp;c. I wiſh e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very naturall man ſeriouſly to conſider this; for thou dying in thy naturall eſtate, art certainely dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and for any thing thou knoweſt thou mayeſt dye the next moment, and then all things are
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:15724:58"/>
thine enimies; death, which is certaine: but how, when, or where, thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not. <hi>Calvin</hi> ſayth, <hi>A man may dye a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand wayes in one houre.</hi> Some Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſay, there are three hundred diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the body, all mortall: Beſides new ſins haue begotten new diſeaſes; &amp; thou mayeſt die ſuddenly by an impoſtume:
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:15724:59"/>
thy houſe may be fiered and thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by it; thy horſe may ſtumble, and ſoe deſtroy thee; a tile may fall as thou art walking, and ſo kill thee; an Adder vnder the graſſe or hearbes may ſting thee. Canſt thou promiſe thy ſelfe to ſee the Sun againe when it's once ſette, though now thou be in
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:15724:59"/>
perfect ſtrength? But however, nature will end at length, Sathan then is ready to come with his vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt malice, when thou art faint and loath to depart; then hee will lay open all thy ſinnes, and then the very next ſtep is,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The Iudgement ſeat of Gods tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, where God will declare what mercy hee offered
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:15724:60"/>
thee, and the Divell will pleade to haue thee.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Then comes the internall ſeparation from God and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of thoſe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which are eaſeleſſe, endleſſe, &amp; remedileſſe. Oh the tearing of the heart, and the gnaſhing of the teeth, that this will produce, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider God every
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:15724:60"/>
Sabbaoth ſtretched out his armes to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace you, and you would not; Chriſt offered to make a plaſter of his hearts blood to cure you, but you trampled it vnder your feete: The holy Ghoſt put good motions into your heart, but you rejected them; the Miniſter hee preſſed hard to haue you yeeld, hut you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:15724:61"/>
him Oh the helliſh cryes that theſe will fetch from ſuch an heart.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Fourth. Act.</label> Wherefore let this betimes begette in thee a baſe eſteeme of thy ſelfe; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>1</label> Thou art worſe then a Toad; nay a Toade is a faire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable creature in compariſon of thee. For firſt, a Toad fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the inſtinct
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:15724:61"/>
of nature, ſerues the Creator in its kinde, it ſuckes vp the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome of the earth, which otherwiſe would poyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs: but thou art a degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate creature &amp; Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who drinkeſt poyſon out of Gods mercy, to ſin more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. Thou art a ſworne friend to his moſt deadly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, and breakeſt all his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:15724:62"/>
Secondly, the venome of a Toad kills but the body: the poyſon of ſinne kills both body and ſoule. Thirdly, When a Toad dyes its mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery is ended, but then thy woe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins; then thou wilt wiſh thou hadſt beene any thing but a man</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>2</label> If thou hadſt look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon that man in <hi>Math.</hi> 8. poſſeſſed
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:15724:62"/>
with a Devill, who dwelt among the Tombes, went na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, chaines would not hold him, the Devill was ſoe powerfull in him: thou wouldſt haue thought him a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſpectacle of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame miſery; to haue a legion of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils by computation ſixe thouſand ſixe hundred ſixtie ſixe: but I tell thee thou
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:15724:63"/>
hadſt better haue a thouſand Legions, then one vnrepented ſinne; for</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The devill he can haue power but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the body, and ſo he may over a Saint, and had over Chriſt to carry him to the top of a Pinnacle: but never ſin, like thine of obſtinate and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall impenitencie, was found in a ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified man.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:15724:63"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Sinne made the divell ſo vgly as hee is, being elſe of an Angelicall nature; onely ſinne makes him odious; therfore it is worſe than a thouſand divels, yea worſe than either the tongue of men and Angells can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> All the divels in hell in thy body, cannot doe the one pinneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth of hurt for
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:15724:64"/>
the ſalvation of thy ſoule: but one ſinne wilfully vnrepented of, and ſo vnpardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, will damne it; ſo that it were better to be poſſeſſed with a thouſand devills, then one ſinne vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of; &amp; vnpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Fifth Act.</label> Get an inward wounding of thine heart and bleeding of ſoule; Where take theſe helpes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:15724:64"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>1</label> Firſt, thy heart that hath beene the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, or rather ſinke from whence haue iſſued many foule ſtreames, where all ill hath beene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, all evill words, raging paſſions, &amp; wicked thoughts; Now then by the rule of proportion, let thy heart be a fountaine of ſorrow for ſinne; If Chriſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen a fountaine of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:15724:65"/>
mercy for mourners, let not vs be exclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for want of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>2</label> Conſider the heart of Chriſt, he had not taken vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> himſelfe a heart of fleſh, but for ſinne, which for thy ſake was tilled with that ſingular depth of ſorrow &amp; griefe, that if all the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorrow of all the Chriſtian ſoules fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:15724:65"/>
world to the end thereof, in heauen or in earth, dead or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, were collected into one heart, they could not counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile the depth of his anguiſh. Shall then his bleſſed ſoule fall aſunder in his bleſſed breaſt, aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with al the wrath of God, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death? Shall his ſoule be like a ſcorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hearth; &amp; ſo preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:15724:66"/>
with the flames of Gods revenging wrath, which wru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g from him thoſe bloody drops and ruefull cryes, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken mee?</hi> The wrath of God was ſo fierce on him, that (I ſay) droppes of blood fell from him: and ſhall thy heart be as a ſtone within thy breaſt, and never be moued? Oh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:15724:66"/>
hardneſſe, and worſe then hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh ingratitude!</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>3</label> If thy heart be not wounded here in ſome meaſure truly, it ſhall hereafter be filled with ſuch end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe horrour, that would grieue and breake ten thouſand hearts to thinke on it. Is it not better then to mourne a little here for ſinne, than to haue our hearts
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:15724:67"/>
inlarged to indure vnto all eternity the horrour of hell? Is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man ſo ſenſeleſſe to thinke he ſhall goe to heaven as in a bed of downe; and never be touched for his ſinne, which is as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, as for thee to reach heaven with thy hand. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Hezekiah</hi> a man per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in all his wayes,<note place="margin">Eſa. 38.14.</note> complained &amp; chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered like a Crane:
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:15724:67"/>
               <hi>David</hi> roared all the day long: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.3. <hi>Iob</hi> complained,<note place="margin">Iob. 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>The arrowes of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are within mee, the venom whereof doth drinke vp my ſpirit.</hi> Nay Chriſt himſelfe cryed out in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gony of his Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>4</label> If thou get this broken heart into thy breaſt, thou ſhalt bring downe the glorious majeſty of heauen; GOD Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:15724:68"/>
with his chaire of State to ſit in thy ſoule; for hee hath two habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.<note place="margin">Eſay. 57.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>1 In heaven.</p>
            <p>2 In an humble heart.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>5</label> Get this and get all. Thou getteſt true title and intereſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the paſſion of Chriſt, and all the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts in the booke of God, the promiſes both of this life, and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:15724:68"/>
of that to come.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Sixt Act.</label> Get an outward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayling with heart-pearcing confeſſion: where</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>1</label> Conſider firſt, the practice of the Saints of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> They powred out teares as men water out of Buckets.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Mary</hi> waſhed Chriſts feete with her teares.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The Publican ſtrucke on his breaſt
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:15724:69"/>
with a ſorrowfull acknowledgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>2</label> Conſider ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thy hands, &amp; eies, and tongue, and heart haue beene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of Gods diſhonour, therefore by rule of proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thou ſhouldſt haue the workes of thy hands inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of repentance; thy eyes fountaines
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:15724:69"/>
of teares; thy tongue ſhould vtter, and heart ſuffer griefe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>3</label> Conſider, that for outward things men will weepe teares, as for dejection from high places, loſſes, croſſes, in wife or children, as <hi>David</hi> for <hi>Abſolon:</hi> ſo it is with many; what wring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their hands, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their haire, bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter crying, &amp;c. Then the loſſe of Chriſt,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:15724:70"/>
who is infinitely better than husband, wife, child, or any thing in the world; this, this, how ſhould it breake thy heart! If all <hi>Iobs</hi> troubles were on thee, and could wring one teare from thee; then one ſinne ſhould wring blood from thy heart.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Seventh Act.</label> Get a hatred and averſion in thy will from ſin, conſidering
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:15724:70"/>
theſe three helpes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> What ſinne is in it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> How God is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked with it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> How thou art hurt by it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>1</label> What ſinne is.</p>
            <p>Sinne in it ſelfe is fouler than any fiend in hell, becauſe it made that ſo; as fire is hotter then water that is heat.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It's extreamely ill, nothing comes
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:15724:71"/>
neare it. I conſider of ſinne here in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract, ſo its a greater ill, than the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a mans ſoule; for when two ills fight together, that which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quers muſt needes be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; now when a man hath lyen in hell ten thouſand yeares, hee is as farre from comming out as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; for the eternall duration in hell can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:15724:71"/>
expiate ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Its moſt infectious, It's compared to a Leproſie; for,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt ſinne that peeped into the world ſtayned the beauty of it; no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſinne was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by <hi>Adam,</hi> but the Stars ſeemed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure in Gods ſight, the beaſts were at variance, the earth full of brambles, and all things curſed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:15724:72"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, it ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all natural, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, and civill acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, if a man in authority be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, all vnder him will be infected.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Sin is moſt filthy, compared to the moſt vile things that can be named; to menſtruous ragges, the vomite of doggs, &amp;c. Nay not any dirt, or filthy thing
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:15724:72"/>
can ſtaine a Sunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beame, but ſin ſtaines a more glorious crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is the ſoule of man.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Sin is of that hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh nature, that it drawes out &amp; takes in, to it ſelfe the wrath of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sin is full of cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed conſequences.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Privatiue.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Poſitiue.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Privatiue, loſſe of Gods favour; the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:15724:73"/>
blood of Chriſt; the guard of Angels; peace of conſcience, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Poſitiue it brings all miſery ſpirituall; hardneſſe of heart, blindneſſe of minde, horrour of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, deſpaire, &amp;c. with all temporall loſſes and croſſes here, and hereafter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall torments of ſoule and body.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>2</label> God is provoked
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:15724:73"/>
with it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Each ſinne is the only object of Gods infinite hatred. His loue is diverſified to himſelfe, his Sonne, the Angels, the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: but his hatred is confined onely to ſinne. What infinite of infinites of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred haſt thou on thy ſoule, with all thy ſinnes, when each ſinne hath the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite hatred of God
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:15724:74"/>
vpon it?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Each ſin is againſt the Majeſty of that dreadfull Lord of Heaven and earth, who can turne all things into hell, nay heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; hell into no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by his word. Now againſt this God thou ſinneſt, &amp; what art thou, but duſt and aſhes, a bagge of filth and flegme, and all that's naught. And what is
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:15724:74"/>
thy life, but a ſpan, a bubble, a dreame, a ſhadow of a dreame? And ſhall ſuch a thing offend ſuch a God?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Every ſin ſtrikes at the glory of Gods pure eye.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Sin is that which killed his Sonne; the leaſt ſinne could not be pardoned but by Chriſts carrying his heart blood to his Father, and offering
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:15724:75"/>
it for ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Each ſinne is an offence to all his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. This aggravated the ſinne vpon <hi>Eli,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.29. <hi>David</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.8.9. &amp;c. Mercy is the moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent attribute of God, and therefore the ſinne againſt it is the greater. What therefore are our ſins in the time of the Goſpell?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>3</label> Conſider how
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:15724:75"/>
thou art hurt by it: for</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Each ſin kills thy ſoule which it better then the world.<note place="margin">Mat. 16.29.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Each ſinne, bring it never ſoe much pleaſure in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting, leaues a threefold ſting:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Naturall.</item>
                  <item>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Temporall.</item>
                  <item>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Immortall.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Naturall, after worldly pleaſure comes melancholly:
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:15724:76"/>
properly either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it laſted no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or they had no more delight in it, &amp;c. That as all wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters end in the ſalt ſea: ſo all worldly joyes are ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp in ſorrowes bottomleſſe gulfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Temporall: ther's labour in getting, care in keeping, and ſorrow in parting with worldly goods.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Immortall: God
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:15724:76"/>
will call thee to judgment for it. Each ſin robbes thee of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. What a vaſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference do we ſee in conquering ſin, and being conquered by ſinne? as for inſtance in <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>David.</hi> the one raiſed after his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſt to much honour; the other, ſcarce enjoyed one good day after hee was conquered; but
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:15724:77"/>
as <hi>Ezekias,</hi> walked heavily in the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ſoule all his dayes. As ſome Divines haue ſaid of <hi>Guliacius</hi> and <hi>Spira,</hi> the one is honour'd in <hi>Calvins</hi> Epiſtles for ever: the other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his backſliding liued a while in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite horror, and after dyed in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Thy owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will accuſe
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:15724:77"/>
thee one day for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſinne, though now it ſeemes hid to thee; and thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is more then a thouſand witneſſes, therefore thou wilt certainely be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> For the ſins which peradventure thou liueſt now in, and accounteſt but petty and veniall, many poore ſoules are at this inſtant burning
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:15724:78"/>
in hell for; What mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and hurt then attends on thee for the ſame?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Eight. Act.</label> Get a ſtrong rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning in thy minde againſt ſinne: as firſt, theſe three grand reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> The horrour of hell; Therefore Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians wrong them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that will not vſe this as a motiue; the vnquenchable wrath of God ſhall
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:15724:78"/>
feede vpon thy ſoule if thou committeſt this ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> The joyes of heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; I ſhall dwell with God for ever, if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving, I make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of every ſin, as an evidence and fruit of ſaving faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> And aboue all, the glory of God: if Gods glory and the damnation of our ſoules were in a bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, his glory
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:15724:79"/>
ſhould preponderate and prevaile, while wee preferre Gods glory aboue our owne ſalvation; <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> would haue done that, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though wee cannot ſeeke it, but in and by our ſalvation, as the meanes is ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to the end.</p>
            <p>Secondly, from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very line in Gods booke:</p>
            <p>His attributes, as
<list>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:15724:79"/>
                  <item>1 His Iuſtice.</item>
                  <item>2 His mercy.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> His Iuſtice to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie ſinners.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> His mercy to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure vs to him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> His Iudgements.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> His Promiſes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, from lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall places: (See <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> on meditations, and in each particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar conſider of thy ſinne.)</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>As 1 The definitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  <item>As 2 The diviſion.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="148" facs="tcp:15724:80"/> As 3 The cauſes.</item>
                  <item>As 4 The effects.</item>
                  <item>As 5 The ſubject.</item>
                  <item>As 6 The adjunct.</item>
                  <item>As 7 The compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</item>
                  <item>As 8 The contrary.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, from places of Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> From examples in Scripture: <hi>How ſhall I do this, &amp; ſo ſin againſt God?</hi> ſaith <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> From your former eſtate; <hi>Yee were dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but now yee are
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:15724:80"/>
light &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> From the end of all things, <hi>Seeing all things muſt be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, what manner of men ought wee to be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, from thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Thy ſoule is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils in hell cannot kill it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Thy body is fraile, all helps cannot long vphold it.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, from Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:15724:81"/>Looke vpon him weeping, nay bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the croſſe, and ſaying thus, <hi>Sinne brought mee from the boſome of my Father to dye for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seaventhly, from the incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble excellencie of God, againſt whom thou ſinneſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Ninth Act.</label> Get a ſincere op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in thy life to ſinne.</p>
            <p>Helpes thereto.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:15724:81"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>1</label> When any bait of Sathan, or old com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure thee to ſin, take this <hi>dilemma:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Either I muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and then it will bring more ſorrow than the pleaſure did good, or not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and then it's the damnation of my ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>2</label> Conſider thy mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which layeſt moſt deſperately in
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:15724:82"/>
one ſcale of the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance heaven, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God, the blood of Chriſt, and thine owne ſoule in the other, a little dung, pelfe, baſe luſt &amp;c. And letteſt this overſway, which bringeth rottenneſſe to thy bones, perhaps loſſe of thy good name &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Helpe. </seg>3</label> And that thou maiſt yet be further armed to withſtand
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:15724:82"/>
the aſſaults of thy three grand enemies, the world, the fleſh, and the devill, which dayly ſeeke the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy ſoule: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider theſe twelue Antidotes:</p>
            <p>Conſider the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the pleaſure of ſin, with the length of the puniſhment, the one for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the other ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Conſider the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:15724:83"/>
of ſinne: for one ſinne never goes alone, but being once entertained, it ſets all the faculties of the ſoule alſo in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion; and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures a ſpirituall judgement, if not temporall, vpon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and perſon.</p>
            <p>Conſider, thy life is but a ſpan, a breath, a blaſt ſoone gone: now if wee had all the pleaſure in the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:15724:83"/>
world, yet being ſo ſoone to looſe it, it's not worth eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Conſider, ſin cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vs to loſe a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter good than that can be, as the favour of God, intereſt in Chriſt, guard of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, right to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Conſider the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; thou maiſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver haue motion to
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:15724:84"/>
repent after thou haſt ſinned, and ſo art damned.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Conſider the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of death to thee; ſome haue liu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out aboue halfe their time, others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all of it; young and old dye ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly many times.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Conſider one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in hell will be worſe then all the pleaſure in the world did good, though it
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:15724:84"/>
ſhould haue laſted a thouſand yeares twice told. So on the contrary, one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in heaven doth more good than all the hardneſſe and paines in good du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or perſecution for them did hurt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Conſider the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of thy ſoule; it's more worth then a world. Loſe it not then for any ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Conſider the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſſe
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:15724:85"/>
of a good conſcience which is a continuall feaſt. This thou loſeſt by ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Conſider, thou ſinneſt againſt a world of mercies, which God hath ſent to thee, as to ſoule, body, good name, eſtate, &amp; others, that belong to thee.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Conſider nothing can waſh away any ſinne but the blood
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:15724:85"/>
of Chriſt. And wilt thou now pollute thy ſelfe againe, as it were to haue him kill'd afreſh to waſh away thy ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> Conſider the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Martyrs and Worthies choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to burne at a ſtake, than they would ſin, and wilt thou ſoe eaſily be drawne to it, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther runne to it? <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelme</hi> ſayd, if the
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:15724:86"/>
flames of hell were on the one ſide, and ſinne on the other ſide, I would rather lye in thoſe flames than ſinne. And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers would rather be torne in pieces with wild horſes. Wee haue as preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous meanes as they, and if our hearts were as good wee ſhould haue the like affections.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Tenth Act.</label> Get a ſincere grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:15724:86"/>
that thou canſt do theſe things no better, as conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Though thou hadſt a thouſand eyes, and could weepe them all out and ſhed ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of teares, and a thouſand hearts to burſt; yet all were not ſufficient for the leaſt ſinne or vanity, either of the eye or heart: How much more when our
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:15724:87"/>
hearts are barren and dry, had wee neede to labour for this ſorrow?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Conſidering when thou haſt made the beſt praier, or watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt diligently o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thy ſelfe, for the right and due ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth, or ſpent thy ſelfe in a day of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation; thou hadſt neede to crye and burſt thy heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:15724:87"/>
for the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and failings thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In this ſorrow, that thou canſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme good duties no better. Weaue vp the web, whats lack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in any of the reſt, here make it vp; and to incourage thee, thou haſt this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe joyned with it, that though thy griefe be ſmall, if it be true, to cauſe thee to
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:15724:88"/>
ſell all: that is, to part from every ſinne for Chriſt, and take him as a husband and a Lord, both for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Then by the conſent of all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines it it godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accepted in Chriſt. ⁂</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15724:88"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
